Okay, so בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, we're going to pick up today
on כ"א עמוד א' Kauf Aleph Amud Aleph in the middle. We're
in the discussion of a בעל קרי, Ba'al Keri, somebody who has
had a seminal emission, what can he and can't he say? But
one of the distinctions in the משנה Mishnah has to do with
saying what's biblical and not, so you can say שמע Shema and
ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon but you cannot say the ברכות Brachot beforehand,
שמע Shema or ברכות Brachot before
eating, and led to a discussion in the גמרא Gemara about the
idea that ברכת התורה Birkat HaTorah was דאורייתא De'oraisa and ברכת המזון
Birkat Hamazon is דאורייתא De'oraisa but not the flip. The ברכות Brachot
afterwards for תורה Torah are rabbinic, ברכות Brachot beforehand for food is
also rabbinic. Now the גמרא Gemara continues with this discussion, again this
related discussion of what's biblical and what's rabbinic because of the issue
of what are we going to allow a בעל קרי Ba'al Keri
to say or to think, so to think in his mind. So
let's take a look now, middle of כ"א עמוד א'. Kauf Aleph
Amud Aleph. אמר רב יהודה. Amar Rav Yehuda. So says רב יהודה,
Rav Yehuda, about twenty lines down beginning of the line. ספק קרא
קריאת שמע ספק לא קרא, Safek kara krias shema safek lo kara,
if somebody doesn't know if they've said the שמע Shema or not.
So they forgot, did I דאוון Daven this one, did I not
דאוון Daven this one, did I say שמע Shema or whatever somehow
they got distracted and they forgot you know they don't remember where
they're up to. So אינו חוזר וקורא. Eino chozer vekorei. You don't
go back and you don't say שמע Shema because that's a little
bit of a shocker but presumably like we're going to see he
says that the שמע Shema is only דרבנן Derabbanan and therefore if
you have a ספק Safek if you've done something rabbinically you don't
have to do it again. ספק אמר אמת ויציב ספק לא אמר,
Safek amar emes veyatziv safek lo amar, but if you don't know
if you said the paragraphs after the שמע Shema leading to the
שמנה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, ספק לא אמר, Safek lo amar, so חוזר
ואומר אמת ויציב. Chozer veomer emes veyatziv. You have to go back
and say the ברכות Brachot after the שמע, Shema, אמת ויציב, Emes
Veyatziv, which is funny you would have thought if anything is rabbinic
it's that. Those are ברכות, Brachot, those were composed by the rabbis.
So the גמרא Gemara says מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason
for this distinction? קריאת שמע דרבנן, Krias Shema derabbanan, אמת ויציב דאורייתא.
Emes veyatziv de'oraisa.
Okay, it tells you קריאת שמע Krias Shema is rabbinic, אמת ויציב
Emes Veyatziv is biblical. Now where is that from? So the אמת
ויציב Emes Veyatziv being biblical is basically because it has the idea
of יציאת מצרים. Yetzias mitzrayim. Right, אמת ויציב Emes Veyatziv talks about
God leading us from Egypt and there's a מצוה Mitzvah למען תזכר
את יום צאתך מארץ מצרים כל ימי חייך. Lemaan tizkor yom tzeischa
meeretz mitzrayim kol yemei chayecha. There's a מצוה Mitzvah to remember יציאת
מצרים Yetzias mitzrayim every day. But why is שמע Shema rabbinic? Doesn't
it say, so this has got to be one of the great
lines in גמרא. Gemara. מתיבי רב יוסף, Matvei Rav Yosef, ובשכבך ובקומך.
Ubeshochavecha uvekumacha. So normally רב יוסף Rav Yosef asks, what about the
פסוק Pasuk ובשכבך ובקומך? Ubeshochavecha uvekumacha? Normally when you have somebody asking
something, challenging a statement, it's from another rabbinic line but here he
just has to quote two words from a פסוק. Pasuk. What do
you mean it's דרבנן? Derabbanan? ובשכבך ובקומך! Ubeshochavecha uvekumacha! So it's a
פסוק. Pasuk. So אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so even though
of course that's what we've all been trained to think for the
last three weeks that this is all biblical, right, nobody's ever suggested
any otherwise. Now all of a sudden we're going to find out
not necessarily. ההוא בדברי תורה כתיב. Hahu bedivrei Torah kesiv. You know
what, maybe it's only talking about learning and teaching תורה Torah like
the פשט Pshat of the פסוק. Pasuk. If we did not have
it internalized in us that there was a מצוה Mitzvah to say
שמע, Shema, we would have read those פסוקים, Pesukim, these you should
teach them, you know, learn them and teach them, when you get
up, when you go to sleep, it means תורה. Torah. So he
says yeah, maybe it means תורה, Torah, maybe all of שמע Shema
is דרבנן. Derabbanan. And therefore if there's a ספק Safek if you've
done it you don't have to redo it, but the last but
the אמת ויציב Emes Veyatziv is biblical because it mentions מצרים. Mitzrayim.
Also the last paragraph of שמע, Shema, of you know ציצית Tzitzis
also mentions מצרים, Mitzrayim, that also if you're not doing if you
haven't done one then the other would still be you know one
aspect of יציאת מצרים Yetzias mitzrayim would be biblical.
Why don't you just say a פסוק Pasuk of יציאת מצרים? Yetzias
mitzrayim? You could. Say the whole אמת ויציב? Emes Veyatziv?
You could. That's an interesting point. Like does the fact that you
have an obligation to זכר יציאת מצרים Zeicher yetzias mitzrayim and ספק
Safek to do it again, does that justify you let's say say,
you're just saying do you have to say it, I would say
does it justify you making the ברכה Bracha about it.
Yeah,
it's
a moving target, what,
why is דאורייתא, De'oraisa, קידוש? Kiddush?
Meaning that's, yeah why is אמת ויציב, Emes Veyatziv,
מצרים, Mitzrayim, right, right.
So that's true, meaning any of those could be, you're right, you
could fulfill your דאורייתא De'oraisa obligation by doing something without the you
know specific text that the rabbis have provided. That's absolutely correct, which
is similar to the point that חיים Chaim just made, which is
like okay, so if you have a ספק Safek just mention יציאת
מצרים. Yetzias mitzrayim. Why do you have to exactly do that text?
Right and nobody's saying that the text per se is
דאורייתא. De'oraisa. Well, no, yes, in this context it's still a דאורייתא
De'oraisa to say it, but the claim isn't that the text per
se... but it's a good point, like would that if you wanted
to say I'll just mention יציאת מצרים, Yetzias mitzrayim, why does it
presumably allow you to make the ברכה? Bracha? Yeah, those are all
good questions. Let's see how the גמרא Gemara continues to develop this.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. תנן. Tenan. Let's see if
you can really sustain that position that שמע Shema is דרבנן. Derabbanan.
Our משנה Mishnah says: בעל קרי מהרהר בלבו ואינו מברך לא לפניה
ולא לאחריה. Ba'al keri meharher belibo ve'eino mevareich lo lefaneha velo leachareha.
That if somebody has had a seminal emission, they think the שמע
Shema but they don't make the ברכות Brachot before and after. ועל
המזון מברך לאחריו ואינו מברך לפניו. Ve'al hamazon mevareich leachareha ve'eino mevareich
lefaneha.
When it comes to food, you say the ברכה Bracha after which
is biblical and not before which is rabbinic. So you see that
the ברכות Brachot after שמע Shema are rabbinic and the שמע Shema
itself is biblical. אי סלקא דעתך אמת ויציב דאורייתא, Ee salka daitach
emet veyatziv de'oraisa, if אמת ויציב emet veyatziv is biblical, לברוך לאחריה,
livroch le'achareha, then you should say the ברכה bracha afterwards because that
is biblical. So the גמרא Gemara says no, מאי טעמא מברך? mai
ta'ama mevarech?
So
the גמרא Gemara says no, why would you make the ברכה? bracha?
You say, we're saying אמת ויציב emet veyatziv is biblical, so you're
saying say it for this בעל קרי. baal keri. Why should you
say it? משום
יציאת מצרים, mishum yetzias Mitzrayim, because of the mentioning of the exodus
which is the biblical aspect of these ברכות? brachos? No, in this
case, we got it covered. הא אדכרה בקריאת שמע. ha adkereh bekerias
Shema. You already said your שמע, Shema, so therefore you don't have
to you don't have to say it. So what they're saying is
אמת ויציב emet veyatziv is biblical when you haven't said יציאת מצרים
yetzias Mitzrayim in another way, when you haven't said the שמע. Shema.
So going back to the original statement, if you don't know if
you said אמת ויציב, emet veyatziv, you have to say it again
is only in a case where you don't know if you said
the שמע. Shema. If you know you've said the שמע Shema but
you forget if you've said אמת ויציב, emet veyatziv, then you don't
have to do it because then you know you've done the biblical
obligation.
So can we ask the same question on the שמע Shema that
the first section of the שמע Shema as we just did with
אמת ויציב emet veyatziv versus say the דאורייתא de'oraisa is the אזכרת
יציאת מצרים hazkaras yetzias Mitzrayim לאו דוקא lav davka that specific? Absolutely.
Or no, because that's actually a quote from the Torah itself whereas
the rabbis composed אמת ויציב. emet veyatziv.
No, no, no. The גמרא Gemara makes no distinction about that. Any
way of mentioning יציאת מצרים, yetzias Mitzrayim, whether quoting biblical text or
not, fulfills the biblical obligation, right? So there's no greater status given
there. But the question is and the way תוספות Tosafos wants to
read the גמרא Gemara is that what might be said was the
following. If I don't know if I've said the שמע, Shema, I
don't know where I'm up to. Wait a minute. Did I start
the שמע, Shema, am I up to אמת ויציב? emet veyatziv? So
then I start with אמת ויציב emet veyatziv because then I'm starting
at the biblical point and if I didn't do the rabbinic part,
I didn't do the rabbinic part. But if I don't know if
I have said the שמע Shema with אמת ויציב emet veyatziv or
haven't said it at all, so there's a biblical obligation floating around
there, right? Because I definitely haven't done the דאורייתא de'oraisa in ציצית
tzitzis and I haven't done it in אמת ויציב. emet veyatziv.
Then I go back and I say, and maybe I say everything
now, right? If you understand תוספות Tosafos reads the גמרא, Gemara, the
גמרא Gemara is saying if you don't know if you said אמת
ויציב, emet veyatziv, you have to go back and say it. That's
only if I also haven't or don't know if I've said the
שמע, Shema, because if I know I've said the שמע, Shema, there's
nothing biblical left of it. So in this scenario where I don't
know if I said the שמע Shema and don't know if I
said אמת ויציב emet veyatziv and I have to go back and
say it, say at least אמת ויציב emet veyatziv anyway, so תוספות
Tosafos reads maybe I go back and say everything now. You got
the case? Once I'm already having to go back and do some
davening, might as well go back and do the, you know, do
the whole package. But that's the case. אמת ויציב Emet Veyatziv is
only biblical in this according to this approach if I haven't said
the פרשת ציצית. parshas tzitzis. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. So the גמרא Gemara says
where are we?
אימא, Eima, so that's true that only the third paragraph is biblical
if one says true, it says like this, so the גמרא Gemara
says ונימא הא ולא ליבעי הא. veneyma ha velo liv'ei ha. So
the גמרא Gemara says okay, so you've got your בעל קרי. baal
keri. He can only do the biblical stuff. Why do we have
him say according to you the שמע, Shema, the middle section? Why
not just have him skip the שמע Shema and do the אמת
ויציב emet veyatziv since that's the biblical section? Either one is biblical.
The question is even on the הרהר בלבו. hirher belibo.
Right, exactly. If you're on הרהר בלבו, hirher belibo, why do the
שמע, Shema, why not just do the אמת ויציב? emet veyatziv? So
the גמרא Gemara says קריאת שמע עדיפא דאית בה תרתי. kerias Shema
adifa d'is bah tartei. קריאת שמע Kerias Shema is better because it
has both. Both what? Presumably it has both the שמע Shema and
the יציאת מצרים. yetzias Mitzrayim. You might as well, and שמע Shema
has עול מלכות שמים. ol malchus Shamayim. So קריאת שמע kerias Shema
always is the bigger package. It's got the דאורייתא de'oraisa of יציאת
מצרים yetzias Mitzrayim and it's got עול מלכות שמים ol malchus Shamayim
and you know the שמע Shema is דאורייתא de'oraisa certainly. But anyway,
if you have to choose that's what you would say. But the
גמרא Gemara still says going back to our case, if you if
you don't know if you said the שמע, Shema, there's no need
to go back because then you can just pick up with אמת
ויציב. emet veyatziv. Okay, you can just continue with אמת ויציב. emet
veyatziv. But if you're a בעל קרי baal keri and you gotta
pick one, better to pick the שמע. Shema. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says רבי אלעזר אומר ספק קרא קריאת שמע ספק לא
קרא חוזר וקורא קריאת שמע. Rebbe Elazar omer safek kara kerias Shema
safek lo kara chozer vekoreh kerias Shema.
He says what we all assume. If you don't know if you
said שמע, Shema, you don't, you have to go back and say
it because that's biblical. ספק התפלל ספק לא התפלל, safek hispallel safek
lo hispallel,
however if you don't know whether you've davened or not, so in
that case אינו חוזר ומתפלל, eino chozer umispallel,
then you don't go back and say שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei because
תפילה tefillah is rabbinic. Now there actually is a debate, I mentioned
this yesterday, between רמב"ם Rambam and רמב"ן Ramban whether תפילה tefillah is
biblical or not, but even רמב"ן Ramban says it's not biblical, or
maybe it's only biblical in a case where a person is in
a time of of צרה tzara of like of anguish of affliction
and he needs to be calling out. So if you're in a
position where the normal human experience is to call out, then you
have to direct those that calling out to God. But other than
that to just regularly pray on a daily basis, there's no biblical
obligation says רמב"ן. Ramban. רמב"ם Rambam says there is. He says that
there's a daily obligation for prayer. But even רמב"ם Rambam says very
clearly it's any words you want, any type of of prayer is
biblical. The whole structure of three times a day a particular text
that's all rabbinic. So in this type of a case that you
don't know if you said the שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, don't
say
it. But then you have an interesting position of ר' יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, which we will hear again more and echo of this later
in this מסכת, Masechet, that ר' יוחנן אומר, Rabbi Yochanan omer, ר'
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, ולואי שיתפלל אדם כל היום כולו. u'levai sheyitpallel
adam kol hayom kulo. I just we I wish that people would
דאוון daven the entire day, which means that there is a value
although there's three times to pray, there is a and that's your
strict obligation, there is a value of praying at any time, even
praying a fixed text. And this becomes this interesting idea, right? Maybe
you could say there's a value of praying at any time that's
like your personal prayer, but if you're going to do the fixed
text, you do it within that the sort of the structure that
the rabbis have created. So there becomes this fascinating debate in the
גמרא Gemara about whether there is a general value of praying not
during the fixed times and if there is that value can it
express itself even in the form of fixed structured prayer or is
that type of stuff best left to the fixed times? So ר'
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says I've got no problem if you want to
דאוון daven all day. So if you have a doubt, it's not
exactly clear what he would say. He certainly wouldn't say that if
you have a doubt if you prayed you shouldn't pray. Would he
say you have to pray or would he at least say it's
a good idea to pray? Number one, maybe you haven't prayed yet
anyway your מנחה, Mincha, right? Most people have a doubt around מנחה
Mincha and מעריב Ma'ariv time, usually not around שחרית. Shacharit. So I
don't remember if I דאוונד davened מנחה Mincha today. So you say
oh don't bother it's only דרבנן. d'rabbanan. Or do we say
look, even if you've דאוונד davened already מנחה Mincha why not do
another דאוונינג? davening? So therefore either you should or it's highly advisable
to do it because you might as well do another דאוונינג davening
anyway even if you haven't and maybe you haven't דאוונד davened מנחה
Mincha then you'll cover your bases and that's basically what ר' יוחנן'ס
Rabbi Yochanan's approach is. Now there's the third approach which is what
we will often tend to say which is this idea about דאוונינג
davening תפילת נדבה. Tefillat Nedavah. You know, do it in a way
that makes it some type of a like of a condition. Like
if I've דאוונד davened already then this should count as an optional
תפילה, Tefillah, if I haven't דאוונד davened it's an obligatory type of
תפילה. Tefillah. That's sort of somewhere striking the middle ground between ר'
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and the first opinion. But anyway, this is the
debate. Do you just say treat it just as an obligation, so
it's rabbinic, you don't know if you've done it, don't do it
again? Or do you try to encourage or obligate to do it
again because it's always good to be praying at all times?
Is that what what was that conditionality addressed?
I guess to דעת. da'at. You know, that gets to a larger
question of can you stipulate what your intention is when you're like
performing certain things. Like I'll give you another example about this in
the context of שמע. Shema.
You're דאוונינג davening שמע Shema
early, like it's בין השמשות bein hashmashos or it's right after שקיעה
shkiah like you דאוון daven you're going to מנחה Mincha מעריב Ma'ariv
and you realize after having learned ברכות Berachot know that it's best
to say שמע Shema with the ברכות. Berachot. But or it's oh
no here's a better example, forget the שמע Shema bit of that.
The example is is that you are ספירת העומר. Sefirat HaOmer. So
you're דאוונינג davening early and you're doing ספירת העומר Sefirat HaOmer because
you're afraid people are going to forget. But you're going to do
it without a ברכה Berachah because it's not really yet the time,
you want to be very פרום, frum, you're going to do it
without a ברכה, Berachah, you're planning on doing it with a ברכה
Berachah later at home. But you got a problem. If you do
it with a ברכה Berachah now, if you do it now without
a ברכה Berachah and you're יוצא, yotzei, then when you want to
do it later and it's definitely nighttime you can't make a ברכה
Berachah because you've already יוצא. yotzei. But you don't want to make
the ברכה Berachah now because maybe it's too early. So what do
you do? So often what people are advised is you do it
now but you stipulate, if I'm יוצא yotzei now if now's the
right time then I don't know I'm sorry you don't do that.
If I remember later to do it to do it with a
ברכה Berachah then
this doesn't count and that one does.
If I don't remember later then this should count and that lets
you later do it with a ברכה. Berachah. Now that all sounds
a little bit of a joke because what is your intent, like
how do you stipulate what your intent is? So anyway but that
often is an attitude that is pretty pervasive in a lot of
these types of scenarios. So that would often be the question as
well about תפילה, Tefillah, like can you stipulate whether to treat your
תפילה Tefillah as a תפילת נדבה Tefillat Nedavah or not? You know,
sort of like you stipulate I don't know to God to to
make the declaration of your intent will have
will hopefully have consequences with how we halachically treat what the act
that was done. But there is a debate of the פוסקים poskim
whether those types of stipulations work. Yes?
Isn't that kind of related to ברירה? breira?
Yeah,
somewhat, yes. Yes, that's true but ברירה breira there's a question about
how ברירה breira works together with תנאי tnai which is way off
topic and I'm not going to get into. Alright, let's take a
look as the גמרא Gemara as the גמרא Gemara continues. So ר'
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says ר' יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan certainly says minimally it
would be advisable to דאוון daven again. Maybe you're even obligated in
that case. He likes the idea of דאוונינג davening a lot. ואמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל, V'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, also רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda says in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, היה עומד בתפילה
ונזכר שהתפלל. hayah omed b'tefillah v'nizkar she'hitpallel. You're standing in תפילה, Tefillah,
right? שמנה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. You got up because you thought you
hadn't דאוונד davened מנחה Mincha and then in the middle you say
oh my God wait a minute I did דאוון daven מנחה Mincha
earlier today. פוסק ואפילו באמצע ברכה. Posek v'afilu b'emtza berachah. You have
to interrupt yourself and sit down. Okay, even in the middle of
a ברכה. Berachah. איני? Ini? says the גמרא, Gemara, is that true?
רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, רב נחמן דהוה יתיב בי רבה בר אבוה,
Rav Nachman de-hava yativ bei Rabba bar Avuha, בעי מיניה הנהו בני
בי רב. ba'ei minei hanehu b'nei bei Rav. When I was at
the house of רב נחמן בר אבוה, Rav Nachman bar Avuha, some
of the students of, literally the children of the house of רב
Rav asked from us, טעו והזכירו של חול בשבת מהו שיגמרו? ta'u
ve-hizkiru shel chol be-Shabbat mahu she-yigmeru? So
if they forget and they remember
they mention, you know, they're דאוונינג davening the חול chol דאוונינג davening
on שבת. Shabbat. So they're just going on autopilot, and they're, you
know, after אתה קדוש Ata Kadosh you're saying אתה חונן לאדם דעת
Ata chonen le-adam da'at and whatever, and somewhere three ברכות brachot in
they realize, wait one minute, שבת. Shabbat.
That's a different case though.
I know, that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. I
know, that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. So what
do they do? מהו שיגמרו? mahu she-yigmeru? Should they finish? ואמר לן,
ve-amar lan, and he said to us,
so I'm sorry, so I think I misstated before. We asked from
him. רב נחמן Rav Nachman said, we asked from רבה בר אבוה
Rabba bar Avuha when הנהו בני בי רב, hanehu b'nei bei Rav,
when like when these kids or whatever forget, apparently it happened right
in the middle, what do they do? ואמר לן, ve-amar lan, and
he said to us, גומרים כל אותה ברכה, gomrim kol ota bracha,
that they go ahead and they finish that ברכה. bracha. They perhaps
wake up and they're in the middle of, I don't know, מברך
השנים, mevarech ha-shanim, they finish מברך השנים mevarech ha-shanim and then they
go back and do, you know, מקדש השבת mekadesh ha-Shabbat and do
the regular שבת Shabbat שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. So don't you see
there that you don't interrupt and sit down? You just continue. So
the גמרא Gemara says like, השתא הכא, hashta hacha, what type of
a comparison is that? התם גברא בר חיובא הוא. hatam gavra bar
chiyuva hu. There you're obligated to be דאוונינג davening שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh
Esrei, but you're דאוונינג davening the wrong text, you're דאוונינג davening the
חול chol text. ורבנן הוא דלא אטרחוהו מקמי כבוד שבת. ve-Rabanan hu
de-la atrichuhu mikamei kevod Shabbat. The רבנן Rabbis did not demand from
you, maybe they didn't want you, they did not demand from you
to say the long שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei on שבת Shabbat because
it would be a טירחא, tircha, it would be demanding a big
דאוונינג davening from you on שבת, Shabbat, not like the ר"ן Ran
was saying שבת Shabbat is when everybody spends all their time in
שול, shul, but also maybe it's not the appropriate text for שבת
Shabbat to be asking personal requests. But nevertheless, you're obligated in a
שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, you're obligated in שחרית, Shacharit, you're דאוונינג davening
a שחרית, Shacharit, it's slightly the wrong text, but it's not completely
inappropriate. So you finish this ברכה bracha and then you continue on
with doing it as if it were שבת Shabbat שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh
Esrei. So there we allow you to finish what you're doing and
then continue. Right? But here, אבל הכא הטעיה היא. aval hacha hat'aya
hi. Here, you've already דאוונד davened מנחה. Mincha. דאוונינג davening again מנחה
Mincha is completely inappropriate for you. So therefore sit down. You find
out you're in the middle of מנחה, Mincha, you've already דאוונד davened
מנחה, Mincha, you shouldn't be דאוונינג davening right now, sit down. Now,
you would think that this would tie into the רב יוחנן Rav
Yochanan discussion before, that רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan would say הלואי שיתפלל
אדם כל היום כולו. halivai she-yitpalel adam kol ha-yom kulo. Who cares?
You've already דאוונד? davened? Finish שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. But
רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot both quote the בה"ג. Behag. If you
look at רש"י Rashi about eight lines from the bottom, כל היום,
kol ha-yom, it starts with the word כל היום. kol ha-yom. בהלכות
גדולות פסק. be-Halachot Gedolot pasak. The הלכות גדולות, Halachot Gedolot, which was
an early גאוני Gaonic פסק psak ספר, sefer, right? הלכה כרב יוחנן
בספק והלכה כשמואל בודאי התפלל. halacha ke-Rav Yochanan be-safek ve-halacha ke-Shmuel be-vadai
hitpallel. We rule like רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan if you have a
ספק, doubt, that presumably means we rule like him that you're obligated,
if you don't know if you've דאוונד davened מנחה, Mincha, go דאוון
daven again because anyway you should be, you know, who cares, דאוון
daven the whole day, that's a voluntary thing. So if you don't
know if you've דאוונד, davened, דאוון daven again. But if you wake
up in the middle of שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei and you realize
you've already דאוונד, davened, sit down. Now what's the difference? If in
the one case I can say I might as well דאוון daven
again because even if I've already דאוונד, davened, another דאוונינג davening can't
hurt, say it in the case when I wake up in the
middle of שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. So here, the way at least
רמב"ם Rambam phrases this and others phrase it is, it's not just
when you wake up in the middle of שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei,
you've already דאוונד davened and therefore you shouldn't be דאוונינג davening again.
There we פסקן pasken like רב יוחנן, Rav Yochanan, might as well
דאוון daven again. The problem is you have defined this דאוונינג davening
as an obligatory דאוונינג. davening. When you got up to start שמונה
עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, you thought you were doing it because you had
to דאוון daven מנחה. Mincha. So you've defined it as an obligatory
דאוונינג, davening, and therefore now that you realize it's not an obligatory
דאוונינג, davening, you've already דאוונד, davened, you can't say, "Oh well, I'm
counting this as an optional דאוונינג, davening, like one of those רב
יוחנן's Rav Yochanan's extra דאוונינגס." davenings. It's already been labeled as an
obligatory דאוונינג, davening, and therefore you know, you're stuck because you're not
obligated, so you might have to interrupt it. Whereas in the case
where you don't know if you've דאוונד davened or not when you
stand up, you realize, "I might not be obligated," so you realize
that the nature of the דאוונינג davening has more of that volitional
aspect to it. Now this sounds very formalistic, but I want to
say that it's not, that it taps into this tension about obligatory
structured prayer and personal volitional optional prayer. Because what we're saying is,
you know, it's a question of like mixing the genres. Right? Those
that argue on רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan don't say it's a bad
idea to be דאוונינג davening all day. They just say we don't
want you to דאוון daven the strict, you know, the structured formal
דאוונינג, davening, that is in its structured time. You want to דאוון,
daven, you say תהלים Tehillim all day, go ahead. But don't דאוון
daven the structured שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, that is for structured prayer.
רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan allows you to use the structured prayer even
in your personal prayer. But what this sort of, this sort of
a compromise is doing is it's saying, as long as you clearly
shape it as a type of a personal prayer, but don't really
mix the, you know, mix the genres. You can't take something that
is in this structured mode and all of a sudden decide you're
going to treat it as a personal prayer. Okay, so even רב
יוחנן Rav Yochanan that lets you use that text it's only when
you're approaching that text as a type of a personal expression. If
you're approaching that text as and doing it as my obligation because
this is what the rabbis say I have to do every day,
you can't then in the middle decide, oh wait a minute, I
want to make that into my personal prayer.
So it's a formalization of כוונה. kavana. That is, your כוונה kavana
informs the meaning of what you're doing. But once you once you
approach with a certain כוונה, kavana,
that
כוונה kavana is in a way provides its structure. And you can't
shift, even if כוונה kavana is everything, you can't
shift in the middle. Exactly. Right. And this idea of how can
you take structured prayer and make it personal in a way that
sort of allows you to use it outside of the structure? So
for ר' יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan it's enough that you approach the prayer
saying, I'm not obligated or I know I might not be obligated
and I'm דאוונען davening anyway. But others say you have to do
something to change it, like we'll see the opinion that you need
to do חידוש דבר, chidush davar, you need to add some personal
words and insert them into the prayer to shape it away from
being strict, sort of obligatory structured prayer. And even though it's mostly
the same text, because you add a little change, you've personalized it
and made it personal. Like the ציבור. tzibur. Right. There you go.
So there is this ongoing tension. It's not like it's either-or. ר'
יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan allows it to be personal if that's the mindset
you approach it in. Okay. Others say no, if it's the straight
text, it never can be personal. But ah, maybe if you change
the text, then maybe we can talk. Okay. So that's what a
lot of this is about.
How about you mentioned the change in מטבע? Matbe'a? The מטבע? Matbe'a?
Well, by שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei they give you more latitude because
שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei itself very much embodies this tension of, like
we said yesterday, why are people, women obligated even though it's fixed
times? רחמי. Rachamei. At its core, it's very personal, and then they
gave it this very objective fixed structure. So that exactly is the
fascinating part of the discussions around prayer is about how that tension
plays out. אמהות. Imahot.
So that becomes a question, as we'll discuss, where are the areas
they allowed you to add and they allowed you to change when
they did when they did give you that latitude. So we'll see
that. Okay. So right now we're just the actual issues about שמונה
עשרה Shmoneh Esrei are really focused on the next פרק, perek, but
here we obviously are beginning to discuss them. So now the גמרא
Gemara continues the following way. It says, ואמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל.
V'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel. So as
we are still talking about דאוונען, davening, and ואמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל, V'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, another statement of רב יהודה אמר
שמואל. Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel. התפלל ונכנס לבית הכנסת ומצא ציבור שמתפללין.
Hispallel v'nichnas l'veit haknesset u'matza tzibur shemitpallelin.
So here you'll see again exactly what I said a second ago.
You went into the שול shul and you found that everybody was
דאוונען. davening. Okay. אם יכול לחדש בו דבר יחזור ויתפלל ואם לאו
אל יחזור ויתפלל. Im yachol l'chadesh bo davar yachzor v'yitpallel v'im lav
al yachzor v'yitpallel.
So I've already דאוונען davened מוסף. Musaf. I went down and דאוונען
davened מוסף Musaf at an early מנין, minyan, I went over to
pick up my wife who is דאוונען davening at the later מנין,
minyan, and everybody there was דאוונען. davening. Okay. So should I just
sit around while everybody's דאוונען davening מוסף? Musaf? Maybe I want to
participate. But I can't participate, I've already דאוונען davened and this is
the fixed obligatory דאוונען. davening. So remember רב יהודה אמר שמואל Rav
Yehuda amar Shmuel did not say like ר' יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. He
didn't say, oh, you can just do the fixed דאוונען davening any
time you want. But here he said, here's where I will let
you do it. אם יכול לחדש בו דבר. Im yachol l'chadesh bo
davar. If I can add some personal, you know,
text to this prayer, I can take the fixed prayer even though
I've דאוונען davened it and make it a personal prayer. And that
will allow me to say the fixed prayer. So the same person,
the same position that said if you remember in the middle of
שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei you've דאוונען davened you have to sit down
even in the middle of a ברכה bracha says that if you
are מחדש בו דבר mechadesh bo davar you can turn it into
personal prayer.
Does this חידוש דבר chidush davar have anything to do with תחנונים
Tachanunim and if it does does it make a difference if it's
Shabbos or not?
I'm sorry, one minute.
Does this אם יכול לחדש בו דבר Im yachol l'chadesh bo davar
refer specifically to בקשה? bakasha?
And if it does, does it matter if it's Shabbos? Because I
shouldn't have given the example of מוסף. Musaf. I gave the example
of מוסף Musaf because I was just trying to think of a
common case. But first of all, מוסף Musaf in general, I should
just mention parenthetically, this whole issue of you can make תפילה tefilla
have a נדבה nedava personal aspect, there's a serious question if you
can do that by מוסף. Musaf. Because מוסף, Musaf, the whole point
of מוסף Musaf is to represent a קרבן. korban. Whereas all other
דאוונען davening is like ערב ובוקר וצהריים, erev vavoker v'tzohorayim, דאוונען davening
at its core, you know, although we link it to קרבנות, korbanot,
its core is the human experience of calling out to God, praying
to God at all at different times during the day. And so
the rhythms of the day, it really does not have to be
related, you know, there could be there is that קרבן korban aspect
too, but it's not wholly defined that way. מוסף, Musaf, we only
say because of קרבנות. korbanot. So according to some, there's no option
of making מוסף Musaf into a תפילת נדבה tefillat nedava and making
it into a personal prayer because it is all about obligatory, all
about קרבנות. korbanot. So number one is I shouldn't have given the
מוסף Musaf example, that's seriously debated. Number two, you asked a good
question about what is חידוש דבר, chidush davar, what is your latitude
of doing חידוש דבר chidush davar in Shabbos where you're not supposed
to have personal בקשה? bakasha?
That's a good question and one could certainly imagine, you know, an
aspect of חידוש דבר chidush davar that is not a
בקשה bakasha personal How much does that then personalize it? That's a
good
question. Normally we do not demand חידוש דבר, Chiddush Davar, so it
doesn't come up so much as a
as long as you have like כוונה Kavanah anyway let me look
into that. That's a good question. Okay.
It's got to be articulated too. It's not מהרהר, Mehirhur, it's not
enough.
Right, although we will see later, that is correct, although we will
see later an interesting debate about what חידוש דבר Chiddush Davar means
and some want to pull it more to just the intentionality aspect.
But right, simply the whole the fundamental debate here between רבי יוחנן
Rebbi Yochanan and רב יהודה אמר שמואל Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel is
רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says as long as you're making it your
own in your mind, that allows you to say a fixed prayer
even not when it's obligated, and רב יהודה אמר שמואל Rav Yehuda
Amar Shmuel says you have to do something to it, you have
to do חידוש דבר. Chiddush Davar. Okay, so then he says דמיהב
אל יחזור ויתפלל De-meihav al yachzor ve-yispalel and if not, don't daven
again because you've already davened and as we know he does not
like you to daven again if you've already davened. So now the
גמרא Gemara says וצריכא, U-tzricha, you need to say both. דאי אשמועינן
קמייתא, De-ee ashmi'inan kamaisa,
had you just said the first thing, that when you wake up
in the middle you've got to sit down, הני מילי יחיד ויחיד,
Hani milei yachid ve-yachid, meaning the גמרא Gemara
for us, when we read the second statement of רב יהודה אמר
שמואל, Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel, the חידוש Chiddush is not that he
says don't say it again, the חידוש Chiddush is that he allows
you to say it again if you add some new text. But
the גמרא Gemara is focusing on the fact that he says don't
say it again if you're just going to say the second thing.
So why do you have to tell me both cases? One case
you say you woke up in the middle of שמונה עשרה Shemoneh
Esrei sit down. One case you say you came to שול, Shul,
don't daven again. You're telling me the same thing. So says, no,
they're not the same. Had you just said the first idea when
you wake up, sit down, in the middle, sit down, that's if
I've already davened private and now I'm davening private again. או ציבור
וציבור, O tzibur ve-tzibur, I davened before in שול Shul and now
I was davening again in שול Shul and I realized in the
middle of my שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei that I've already davened. Since
it's the exact same experience as last time, sit down even in
the middle. אבל יחיד לגבי ציבור, Aval yachid legabi tzibur, I might
have thought that if I davened at home and then I came
to שול Shul and they were standing שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, that's
a different experience. And even though I've already fulfilled my obligation and
even if I'm not going to make it personal, maybe I do
another שחרית Shacharis because it's like oh now I can get a
better שחרית. Shacharis. So I'll do a שחרית Shacharis again because I
can make it better, even as an obligation, not even as a
personal prayer. So כמאן דלא צלי דמי, Ke-man d'la tzalay dami, maybe
vis-a-vis that it's like I haven't davened. קא משמע לן. Ka mashma
lan. So that's why שמואל Shmuel had to tell me that even
if I come to שול, Shul, I davened at home and I
come to שול, Shul, I don't daven again even though now I
can get it with the ציבור. Tzibur. That I don't do again.
ואי אשמועינן הכא, Ve-ee ashmi'inan hacha, and if you so why not
tell me the שול Shul example, you come to שול Shul don't
do it again? משום דלא אתחיל בה, Mishum d'la at-chil bah, because
that I would say don't start with the שול Shul because you
have don't start, you've already davened. אבל התם דאתחיל בה, Aval hasam
d'at-chil bah, but I would think if I'm in the middle of
שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei and I wake up in the middle, I'm
already in the middle, you might as well finish. אימא לא, Eima
lo, don't interrupt, don't stop, continue doing it. צריכא, Tzricha, you have
to tell me both. So when it comes to the context of
obligatory structured prayer, רב יהודה אמר שמואל Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel does
not want you to repeat it under any circumstances. Even if you're
in the middle and you're already in the middle, even if you
had only davened before private and now you find yourself in a
שול, Shul, whatever cases are, if it's in the context of obligatory
again, you never do an obligatory again, right? You would sit down
in the middle even though you now have the option of doing
it with the ציבור, Tzibur, anything, sit down in the middle. But
the other thing that Mordechai highlighted is he gives you a way
to make structured prayer into personal prayer, and that's by חידוש דבר
Chiddush Davar and that does allow you to do it again because
then you're doing a different type of prayer. Okay. So these are
like great fundamental concepts about this tension between the human experience of
prayer and the core sense of prayer and then the structured rabbinic
prayer that's put on top of it, and they will really play
out as we continue. Right now it's in a digression of a
larger discussion here about כמאן דבאל קרי, Ke-man d'ba'al keri, which the
גמרא Gemara will be getting back to soon, but not yet. So
let's take a look.
Why for example is it given in terms of a different experience?
You used the word experience a number of times in your translation
and discussion. It's actually textual. No, what if you davened at home
and you davened like you davened at home, and you come to
שול Shul and there's somebody with a beautiful voice and there's a
different experience. It's obviously a different experience.
So that's the question that Dov asked before, what constitutes חידוש דבר?
Chiddush Davar? So when we get this there is a משנה Mishnah
later that will be like a focus of a discussion about חידוש
דבר Chiddush Davar and
about, so I'm going to bracket that for now. Okay, but you're
right, meaning can you have חידוש דבר Chiddush Davar that's not by
adding text?
And if we can even expand it, you have dinner with your
spouse every night, right? But each time is a different experience. Right.
Right. So that is exactly the discussion later on. Can חידוש דבר
Chiddush Davar just be that you're bringing a whole different type of
an inner experience to the event? Okay. And that is exactly will
be a discussion later on. Okay. So let's, so now let's see
what the גמרא Gemara goes on, turns to next within this discussion.
אמר רב יהודה הנכנס לבית הכנסת. Amar Rav Yehuda hanichnas l'veit haknesset.
So since we talked about coming to שול shul and finding they
were דאווענינג davening and you've already דאווענד, davened, what do you do?
We're going to have another scenario. הנכנס לבית הכנסת ומצא ציבור שמתפללים.
Hanichnas l'veit haknesset umatzah tzibur shemitpalelim. You come and they're דאווענינג davening
and you haven't דאווענד davened yet. So there they are, they're in
אז ישיר Az Yashir and you've got to get started with the
ברכות השחר. Birchas HaShachar. So, אם יכול להתחיל ולגמור עד שלא יגיע
שליח ציבור למודים, יתפלל. im yachol lehatchil uligmor ad shelo yagia shliach
tzibur l'Modim, yitpallel. ואם לאו, אל יתפלל. v'im lav, al yitpallel. Now
it's not worried about my scenario because as I said, according to
the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא Gemara primarily just knows about שמע Shema
and שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. All the rest of it, I mean
it knows about ברכות התורה Birchas HaTorah we mentioned, but you know
so much of that gets sort of filled in later. So basically
what it's talking is I'm coming and let's take an easy example,
I don't even need to worry about שמע. Shema. מנחה. Mincha. I
come, they're in the middle of שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. Do I
start שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei now or not? So you know what's
the concern? If I start, if I don't do שמונה עשרה Shmoneh
Esrei I'm going to miss תפילה בציבור. tfila b'tzibur. But if I
start שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei they'll be done before I'm done and
I'm going to miss קדושה. Kedushah. So what do I do? So
this question is exactly what the גמרא Gemara is asking. Okay. So
אם יכול להתחיל ולגמור עד שלא יגיע שליח ציבור למודים. im yachol
lehatchil uligmor ad shelo yagia shliach tzibur l'Modim. Interestingly though it doesn't
mention קדושה. Kedushah. It mentions מודים. Modim. We'll discuss why. If I
can finish before they get to מודים, Modim, יתפלל, yitpallel, then jump
in, start now, and then at least I'll be able to כאפ
chapp מודים Modim with them. ואם לאו אל יתפלל. v'im lav al
yitpallel.
But if not, don't. You don't want to be in שמונה עשרה
Shmoneh Esrei when they're doing מודים. Modim. Interestingly, not concerned about קדושה.
Kedushah. רב יהושע בן לוי אומר אם יכול להתחיל ולגמור עד שלא
יגיע שליח ציבור לקדושה. Rav Yehoshua ben Levi omer im yachol lehatchil
uligmor ad shelo yagia shliach tzibur l'Kedushah. No, you have to be
ready to do קדושה Kedushah with them. So if you can finish
before they say קדושה, Kedushah, then יתפלל, yitpallel, then דאוון daven with
them. ואם לאו אל יתפלל, v'im lav al yitpallel, and then not,
not. So במאי קמיפלגי, b'mai kamifligi, what are they debating? מר סבר
יחיד אומר קדושה ומר סבר אין יחיד אומר קדושה. Mar savar yachid
omer Kedushah umar savar ein yachid omer Kedushah. What, the question is
can you say your own private קדושה Kedushah in your שמונה עשרה?
Shmoneh Esrei? There I am, I'm דאווענינג davening with them, can I,
I mean I'm דאווענינג, davening, they're ahead of me, I'm not going
to get my קדושה Kedushah with them, they'll be at קדושה Kedushah
before I'm done. When I get up to הקל הקדוש, HaKel HaKadosh,
can I just insert קדושה Kedushah into my private שמונה עשרה? Shmoneh
Esrei? That's a shocker. So apparently there's those that say that, and
they're like I can insert a קדושה, Kedushah, maybe it's when I
totally דאוון daven private, maybe it's when I'm דאווענינג davening and I'm
not synced with them but there's a מנין minyan around me, but
there is this opinion that I can say a קדושה Kedushah in
my שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. So therefore I don't have to worry
so much that I'm not participating with their קדושה. Kedushah. But I
do have to worry about מודים. Modim. The other says you can't
say קדושה Kedushah in your שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, you do have
to worry. So we'll talk, let's finish this discussion and then I'll
reflect back on some of the points there like why is מודים
Modim so important and so on. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. וכן אמר רב אדא בר אהבה. V'chein amar Rav Adda bar
Ahava. מניין שאין יחיד אומר קדושה. Minayin she-ein yachid omer Kedushah.
How do you know you don't say קדושה Kedushah privately? And this
really seems to be that there was a position that you could
say it completely in a private שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei with no
ציבור tzibur around at all. How do you know you need a
ציבור tzibur for קדושה? Kedushah? שנאמר Shene'emar because it says: ונקדשתי בתוך
בני ישראל. v'nikdashti b'toch Bnei Yisrael. I'll be sanctified amongst the children
of Israel. כל דבר שבקדושה לא יהא פחות מעשרה. Kol davar she-bikdusha
lo yihiyeh pachos me-asara.
Any matter of קדושה, Kedushah, of sanctifying God's name, is בתוך בני
ישראל, b'toch Bnei Yisrael, is with a מנין minyan with ten. And
this is the whole idea, this is the core גמרא, Gemara, I
mean it's based on a משנה Mishna in מגילה Megilla that says
all the things you need ten for, but this is the concept
that you need a מנין, minyan, you need ten for דברים שבקדושה.
devarim she-bikdusha. And then the question of course comes what is דברים
שבקדושה? devarim she-bikdusha? And often you find that it becomes a sort
of a circular argument. Oh, דברים שבקדושה devarim she-bikdusha so you need
a מנין minyan for it. So that's like a very serious question
of how do you define what is דברים שבקדושה? devarim she-bikdusha? But
here it's not a big jump to say קדושה Kedushah is דברים
שבקדושה. devarim she-bikdusha. The whole thing about קדוש קדוש קדוש Kadosh Kadosh
Kadosh and ונקדשתי v'nikdashti and declaring God as holy, that is clearly
דברים שבקדושה, devarim she-bikdusha, you need a מנין, minyan, so don't go
telling me you can say it ביחיד. b'yachid. Yes.
Those are just quotes from
נביא.
Navi. ונקדשתי בתוך בני ישראל? V'nikdashti b'toch Bnei Yisrael? No, it's from
ויקרא. Vayikra. קדוש קדוש קדוש.
Kadosh Kadosh Kadosh.
קדוש קדוש קדוש, Kadosh Kadosh Kadosh, yes.
Yeah, so I can't read that out loud when I'm reading through
the נביא? Navi?
Okay, so yes you can, and that gets to a question about
when you frame things as פסוקים psukim as opposed to being framing
them as a type of a liturgy. So the best example about
this is why in סליחות, Selichos, right, that saying, right, ה' ה'
קל רחום וחנון Hashem Hashem Kel Rachum v'Chanun which is considered to
be דברים שבקדושה. devarim she-bikdusha. So if you're doing סליחות Selichos ביחיד
b'yachid you can do it, but they say two things. To turn
it into a פסוק pasuk and not make it the liturgy which
is דברים שבקדושה. devarim she-bikdusha. Number one is you're supposed to do
it with the טראפ. trop. Okay, although of course you could read
a פסוק pasuk without a טראפ, trop, it's still reading a פסוק,
pasuk, but they emphasize that it's being treated as a פסוק pasuk
and not as like a דברים שבקדושה. devarim she-bikdusha. And you end
it in the middle normally, you know, ונקה לא ינקה v'nakeh lo
yenakeh when that is because of its liturgical use. If you're saying
it as a פסוק pasuk you end it. So you completely, which
is not something you want to be saying during סליחות, Selichos, right,
פוקד עוון אבות על בנים, pokeid avon avos al banim, but anyway,
but that's what they say if you're doing it ביחיד. b'yachid. So
yes, could you say קדוש קדוש? Kadosh Kadosh? Yes. But you can't
say it in the middle of שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei as
a
דברים... devarim...
you
know as a liturgy, that then becomes a דברים שבקדושה. devarim she-bikdusha.
Yes. Some other פוסק postek says...
That's true, that is true, although there for some reason people aren't
as מקפיד makpid on it, but probably because I don't know, it's
a good question, probably because that even when we say it בציבור,
betzibur, although everybody sort of says it together, it's not somehow as
ritualized as much, so there's not which it is דבר שבקדושה, davar
shebekedusha, and also the קדוש kadosh that you say before the שמע,
shema, right? Yes, all of those are, but I think that the
reason we don't feel a need to change the experience so much
is because even when we do it בציבור, betzibur, it's it's not
as ritualized as like the קדושה. kedusha. So it doesn't feel if
I told a normal person who had learned this when you say
the קדוש קדוש kadosh kadosh in the שמע shema beforehand, it's דבר
שבקדושה, davar shebekedusha, it's like saying the קדושה, kedusha, they'd think I'm
crazy. It just feels like reading פסוקים, psukim, you know? So you
are correct, you know, technically, but it gets back to Charlie's point,
which is there's no you know, if it's פסוקים psukim and it
feels like פסוקים, psukim, we don't you know then we then you
know we let it go. Yeah, I'm staying then here just...
That is true.
So that whole question of where did the idea that a מנין
minyan requires men, I mean we learn out how you learn בתוך
בני ישראל betoch bnei yisrael is ten from you know by the
from the עדה, edah, the קורח, Korach, מתוך העדה mitoch ha-edah and
so on. So there happened to be men, it's כולם אנשים kolam
anashim and so on, but the גמרא Gemara you are here says
עשרה asara and not ten and not only here it says ten
it says עשרה דברים, asara devarim,
but it's
no
no no, no text says דברים devarim as far as I know.
And what, look on the bottom, but what
who I'm sorry?
I understand. He says that there are manuscripts of the גמרא Gemara
that say that? No. No. Okay, the פוסקים poskim say that. That's
right, right, right! So there is yes yes yes, there is when
the גמרא Gemara says ten it never mentions men. That is absolutely
correct, right, that is correct. And yes, it makes it like you're
reading פסוקים. psukim. Well those are not דבר שבקדושה davar shebekedusha though,
I mean they're מצוות, mitzvos, yes, but
the דבר שבקדושה davar shebekedusha in the sense
of the as
requiring a מנין minyan for their recital, those that's
not true about the שמע shema and the but I
guess your point is does the saying with the טראפ, trop, meaning
forget the technical
question, reshape the experience as a non-liturgy experience and as a like
reading of a text experience? That's an interesting point. But by the
שמע, shema, the שמע shema is you're quoting the תורה. Torah. It's
called קריאת שמע, kriat shema, so the whole experience is reading biblical
text whereas saying the קדושה kedusha is scripting a dramatic reenactment as
if you are there at that moment. Nice way of saying it,
right. And they do say also that there the value of saying
the שמע shema with the טראפ trop as we learned before about
being מדקדק medakdek by the קריאת שמע, kriat shema, so the טראפ
trop helps you put the right emphasis and the right pauses and
so on. But I think Dov's point is really is really on
target as well, that קריאת שמע kriat shema is קריאת שמע kriat
shema is the reading of biblical text whereas this is not treating
the text as text. Right. And what do you want to say
קידוש? kidush? Yeah, קידוש kidush is interesting. קידוש, kidush, I was קידוש,
kidush, do people say the טראפ trop by קידוש? kidush? קידוש kidush
is also ויהי ערב ויהי בקר יום הששי... vayehi erev vayehi voker
yom hashishi... no when you say that that's a ניגון, niggun, that's
not the טראפ. trop. ויכלו השמים והארץ וכל צבאם ויכל אלקים, Vayechulu
hashamayim veha-aretz vechol tzeva'am vayechal elokim, that's a ניגון, niggun, that's not
טראפ. trop. Who do the טראפ trop for that? Really? Okay that's
I really haven't heard that. All right, that I haven't heard. All
right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. All right, so
okay, now מאי משמע, mai mashma, where do you get that this
is ten? So the גמרא Gemara goes on, דתני רבנאי אחוה דרב
חייא בר אבא, detani Ravnai achu'ei derav Chiya bar Abba, אתיא תוך
תוך, asya toch toch, a גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah, תוך תוך. toch
toch. כתיב הכא ונקדשתי בתוך בני ישראל ketiv hacha venikdashti betoch bnei
yisrael וכתיב התם vechtiv hatam it says over there, הבדלו מתוך העדה
הזאת. hibadlu mitoch ha-edah hazos. Separate yourself from the middle of this
congregation by קורח, Korach, by the מרגלים. meraglim. מה להלן עשרה אף
כאן עשרה, mah lahalan asara af kan asara, the same way there
are ten here too are ten. And again it's correct it does
not mention women and that becomes an interesting discussion in the ראשונים.
rishonim. The ראשוני אשכנז rishonei ashkenaz discuss a woman as the tenth.
רמב"ם Rambam never explicitly excludes women. רמב"ם Rambam says that רמב"ם Rambam
says that רמב"ם Rambam says that that a מנין minyan is made
up of ten עשרה גדולים בני חורין. asara gedolim bnei chorin. And
he does not he so some people want to argue since he
says it in the masculine he says בני חורין bnei chorin he
means men but the רמב"ם Rambam never explicitly excludes women. The שולחן
ערוך Shulchan Aruch explicitly excludes women but that's not the גמרא. Gemara.
I should also mention that because we learn it out from the
עדה edah of the מרגלים, meraglim, when רב משה Rav Moshe is
asked about counting like non-observant Jews and מחללי שבת mechalelei shabbos and
whatever, although in some places רב משה Rav Moshe is very strict
about excluding you know sort of non-observant Jews for certain things, here
he says, "ah, since we learn it out from the מרגלים meraglim
and there they were all רשעים, reshaim, so that counts!" It says
somewhere העדה הרעה הזאת ha'eidah hara'ah hazot and so that's what we
learned, that's one of the sources. Yeah, I know. But this is
right. No, but the עדה מתוך עדה eidah mitoch eidah here is
מרגלים. meraglim. העדה הרעה הזאת ha'eidah hara'ah hazot if I remember correctly
is קרח, Korach, right? Anyway, but it doesn't matter. The מרגלים meraglim
were also רשעים reshaim according to that. So we learn it out.
Fine. Now the גמרא Gemara goes on. מה להלן עשרה אף כאן
עשרה. ma lehalan asarah af kan asarah. כולי עלמא מיהא מפסיק לא
פסיק. kulei alma miha mafsik lo fasik. So everybody would agree that
you don't interrupt your שמנה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. The whole question is:
can you finish in time for קדושה Kedushah or finish in time
for מודים? Modim? But nobody says you would interrupt your שמנה עשרה
Shemoneh Esrei to say that. So now they want to ask, okay,
you don't interrupt your שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei for מודים Modim or
קדושה. Kedushah. That we've agreed. Now we have another question though. איבעיא
להו: ibaia lehu: מהו להפסיק ליהא שמיה הגדול מבורך?
mahu lehafsik le-yehei shemeih hagadol mevorach? Can you interrupt for יהא שמיה
רבא מבורך? yehei shemeih raba mevorach?
Here they have it a little bit in Hebrew: יהא שמיה הגדול
מבורך. yehei shemeih hagadol mevorach. That was seen responding to יהא שמיה
רבא yehei shemeih raba and as
Joe pointed out nicely the other day, it's almost a direct translation
of, you know, כי שם ה' אקרא הבו גודל לאלהינו, ki shem
Hashem ekra havu godel l'eloheinu, which is יהא שמיה הגדול מבורך. yehei
shemeih hagadol mevorach. That's giving גודל. godel.
So whatever, is that response, that might be so important that you
interrupt your שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei if people are if the ציבור
tzibur is saying יהא שמיה רבא. yehei shemeih raba. So do you
do it or not? So let's take a look. כי אתא רב
דימי אמר רב יהודה אמר רב שמעון, ki ata Rav Dimi amar
Rav Yehuda amar Rav Shimon, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב שמעון תלמידי
דרבי יוחנן אמרי. amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav Shimon talmidei de-Rabbi Yochanan
amri. Rav Yehuda and Rav שמעון לקיש, Shimon Lakish, the students of,
excuse me, Rabbi יוחנן Yochanan say: לכל אין מפסיקין חוץ מיהא שמיה
הגדול מבורך. le-chol ein mafsikin chutz mi-yehei shemeih hagadol mevorach. Everything you
do not interrupt except for יהא שמיה רבא. yehei shemeih raba. ואפילו
עוסק במעשה מרכבה פוסק. ve-afillu osek be-ma'aseh merkavah posek. Even if you
are dealing with the heavenly chariot, you are in some high ecstatic,
kabbalistic, you know, mystical mode, you interrupt for יהא שמיה הגדול מבורך.
yehei shemeih hagadol mevorach. ולא הלכתא כוותיה. ve-lo hilchata kavateih. We don't
rule like that. You do not interrupt even for יהא שמיה רבא.
yehei shemeih raba. Now I have to tell you, it's not clear.
Clearly the גמרא Gemara gives an enormous amount of weight to this.
Obviously the possibility you interrupt שמנה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. You might remember
going back to the first פרק perek that we had that lovely
אגדתא aggadata by the חורבא churva where, you know, the desolate houses,
and אליהו Eliyahu was waiting for him. And the whole story that
God says, you know, when my children now say, you know, יהא
שמיה הגדול מבורך, yehei shemeih hagadol mevorach, or you know, they say,
'Praises the King,' you know, that his children, you know, praise him
in his palace this way. So the יהא שמיה הגדול yehei shemeih
hagadol is sort of seen as this amazing, you know, moment of
the liturgy that's extremely powerful. But it's fascinating. First of all, we
haven't even seen it discussed that you're supposed to say it. It's
so taken for granted that you say it. But number two also,
like, why is that giving greater weight than like קדוש קדוש קדוש
kadosh kadosh kadosh and so on? Again, it's like, you know, it's
taken for granted. I really don't know, you know, why that assumption
is made. In the end we don't allow it to interrupt שמנה
עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, but it doesn't mean that we're not seeing this
as probably the most central type of ציבור tzibur experience of declaring
the greatness of God, you know, or the majesty of God, more
than everything else. Do you have any thoughts about that? About why
this is given so much more weight? Is it just the line
in the קדיש? Kaddish? יהא שמיה רבא מבורך, yehei shemeih raba mevorach,
right. I don't know. I just know that it is. Right. Right.
I mean, the one thing I could think about also is that
since it also plays into, like, you know, a sense of a
קדיש—I Kaddish mean, that becomes a question of like, when its function
in קדיש Kaddish in the דאוונען, davening, when the function in terms
of קדיש יתום. Kaddish yatom. But the fact that it's also said
in response to tragedy, and it's basically a sense of always acknowledging
God's greatness, even in, you know, even like, you know, in the
worst of times, you know, has a—you know, that's central. It's primal.
Yeah, the גלוי gilluy is primal. You said it was in response
to learning תורה. Torah. Right. So and the context of the of
the what do you call it? Of like the ברכת התורה Birkat
HaTorah that we said the other day. But yeah, okay. Charlie, what
did you want to say? This is in Hebrew, but we say
it in—I know, I know. So that's also a question, when did
that liturgy change to be the to be the Aramaic? It's so
widespread. I mean, like, להבדיל, lehavdil, ninety-nine to the—it's a central theme
in Sermon on the Mount and elsewhere in the New Testament, which
was written by Jews. What the Church Fathers later called it a
Testament was written by Jews. Right, right, sure. It's completely widespread, the
doxology, the New Testament. יהא שמיה רבא. yehei shemeih raba. Really? Yeah.
What does it translate? Sanctified be the Lord's name or something like—Our
Father, sanctified be—hallowed be thy name. Right. יהא שמיה. yehei shemeih. No
question. The Greek translation of the יהא שמיה רבא. yehei shemeih raba.
Really? Okay. כי אתא רב דימי אמר רב יהודה אמר רב שמעון.
ki ata Rav Dimi amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav Shimon. You postpone
even ברכת המזון? Birkat HaMazon? שמנה עשרה? Shemoneh Esrei? Not that. Let
me say. Let me just. Wait. We're going 8:30 now, right? Has
the new time officially changed already? Okay, fine. So... So let me,
let me, let me say a couple things here about the מודים
Modim though and why it's important. So why is the מודים Modim
so important to get up to the מודים? Modim? So you could
have said it has to do with the text of the מודים,
Modim, מודים אנחנו לך, Modim anachnu lach, basic expression of, you know,
gratitude to God for everything God has given us is something that
you want to participate with with the ציבור tzibur and that is
the power of it. However, רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosfos both point
out that it's not actually the text of מודים Modim which is
so important to be participating with, it is the experience of the
bowing down. If you take a look at רש"י Rashi and תוספות
Tosfos repeats this where it says, one minute, let's take a look.
It's like three lines down in the narrow lines, רש"י Rashi says,
or first narrow line, אבל מודים אף על פי שיחיד אומר מודים,
aval Modim af al pi she-yachid omer Modim, even though you say
מודים Modim in your own שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, so why is
it important to finish in time that they're finishing? אם אינו אומרו
עם הציבור, im eino omro im ha-tzibur, if you're not saying it
when they're saying it, you're in the middle of your שמונה עשרה
Shemoneh Esrei and they're saying מודים, Modim, הרואה כולם כורעים והוא אינו
כורע, נראה ככופר במי שחבריו משתחוים לו. ha-ro'eh kulam kor'im ve-hu eino
koreia, nireh ke-kofer be-mi she-chaveirav mishtachavim lo. They're bowing down to God,
they're doing מודים Modim and you're standing up. So the problem is
not that it's the text of מודים Modim is important to say
with the ציבור, tzibur, it's the experience of bowing down that one
wants to do with the ציבור. tzibur. Which suggests a solution, which
is what's the solution? דאווען Daven שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei and bow
down when they're up to it. So look at תוספות. Tosfos. תוספות
Tosfos says עד שלא יגיע ציבור למודים. ad she-lo yagiia tzibur le-Modim.
So first he quotes רש"י Rashi and then he says like this:
והוא הדין נמי, ve-hu ha-din nami, it's like the third line of
תוספות, Tosfos, אם יגיע למודים כששליח ציבור יגיע למודים. im yagiia le-Modim
kshe-sheliach tzibur yagiia le-Modim. Let's say you're up to your מודים Modim
when they're up to their מודים. Modim. You're not done with שמונה
עשרה Shemoneh Esrei but you've synchronized your מודים Modim with theirs. דשפיר
דמי כיון שמשתחוה עם חבריו, deshappir dami kivan she-mishtachaveh im chaveirav, okay,
but you can never time it. Then it says that three lines
down in the narrow lines, רבינו תם היה רגיל כשהיה מתפלל ביחיד,
Rabbeinu Tam haya ragil kshe-haya mitpallel be-yachid, meaning ביחיד be-yachid because he
wasn't up to where the ציבור tzibur was up to, כשחזן מגיע
למודים, היה כורע עם הקהל, ולא אמר כלל. kshe-chazzan magiia le-Modim, haya
koreia im ha-kahal, ve-lo amir klal. So don't say מודים, Modim, just
bow. So it looks like you're bowing the same way remember we
said about saying the שמע Shema silently in your mind. Because they're
doing שמע Shema you should do שמע, Shema, which
also leads to the practice
nowadays that you're somewhere in the middle and they're up to שמע,
Shema, you put your hand over your eyes, you make it look
like you're participating. You don't want to look like they're saying שמע
Shema and you're not. You don't want to look like
they're bowing down in מודים Modim
and you're not. So you bow down, don't have to say anything,
just bow down. Which of course raises the question why didn't the
גמרא Gemara think of that?
But okay. But that actually becomes the general practice is what רבינו
תם Rabbeinu Tam said. And then he says, but you can't, there's
certain points in שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei you're not supposed to bow
down, but basically that's what you do. And then he says, then
he says, now that we're so that's in terms of the מודים
Modim concern of the גמרא. Gemara. How about the קדושה Kedusha concern
of the גמרא? Gemara? The גמרא, Gemara, you know, says that it
seems like the conclusion of the גמרא Gemara is, since you don't
say your own private קדושה, Kedusha, you only start if they, if
they're able to finish in time for קדושה, Kedusha, but you know,
sometimes you think you'll finish, sometimes you won't or whatever. How about
just silently listening to קדושה? Kedusha? There the issue is the text
itself, not the experience of bowing down. But here he quotes רש"י
Rashi and there's a רש"י Rashi that says that, okay, so be
silent for קדושה Kedusha and be יוצא: yotzei: שומע כעונה. shomeia ke-oneh.
You heard, it's like you said, so you can also דאווען daven
even and get in the קדושה Kedusha by just silently attending. So
תוספות Tosfos debates whether if you can be יוצא yotzei that way
maybe it's considered an interruption in your שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. No,
because we're not calling bowing down as if you spoke. If the
reason you're יוצא yotzei by listening, but you're still during the problem,
I understand, but we're not talking about distraction being the problem, there's
a problem about speaking in the middle of שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei
as a הפסק. hefsek. So if listening counts as speaking, does it
interrupt? Now obviously like the גמרא Gemara said before, it could count
enough that you're יוצא, yotzei, it counts as if you said, but
you didn't actually say, it doesn't actually interrupt. So now and in
the end תוספות Tosfos comes along to that conclusion. So then what
we wind up is the גמרא Gemara that basically says don't get
started, you need to bow down for מודים, Modim, you need to
say קדושה. Kedusha. And תוספות Tosfos got two solutions: bowing down for
מודים, Modim, no problem, just bow down, don't say anything. Saying קדושה,
Kedusha, no problem, just listen, you're יוצא. yotzei. And then, so maybe
לכתחילה lechatchila it's a little bit of a question. לכתחילה lechatchila should
you start if you know you're going to have those problems? Because
the גמרא Gemara sounds like לכתחילה lechatchila you shouldn't start. But if
you find yourself in those situations, תוספות Tosfos has a solution for
you. Yes. Is there an implication here that this isn't such a
private public thing because people looking at you instead of doing their
own? If you're really דאווענינג davening you're not supposed to be looking
at who's bowing down, who's hands are over whose eyes. You're supposed
to be having a relationship with השם. Hashem. Maybe not the same
relationship you have on the mountains, with the lakes. Right, right, right.
But what are you doing looking to see who has a hand
over or who's bending or who's? Right, right. It's true. Okay, but
I understand and you know be better to pray ביחיד. be-yachid. And
then with the ציבור, tzibur, יחיד yachid is you and God, right?
Well, that does become an interesting discussion in the פוסקים, poskim, which
is if I can have more כוונה kavanah ביחיד be-yachid should I
do that more than with a ציבור? tzibur? And some say yes,
some say no, but by the way... Right, that everybody's sort of
peripherally aware of eye coffee. Of what? Eye coffee. Okay, yes. And
what about in עלינו? Aleinu? Where we also bow down if you're
in the middle of your praying and they bow down. Yeah, and
that's a good point too, by עלינו Aleinu as well, the bowing
down if everyone else is. It should look like they're all bowing
down. And there it's even more explicit. By מודים Modim you're just
saying we're thanking you. By עלינו Aleinu the whole point is we
don't bow down to false idols, we bow down to you God.
So yes, there too, the idea of going along in the bowing
down even if you're not saying עלינו. Aleinu. But תוספות Tosafot at
least does say that you're not supposed to, לכתחילה lechatchila you're supposed
to obviously do it directly, which is what this משנה Mishnah says.
But if you find yourself in the middle of שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh
Esrei, there are solutions. Okay, so now we go on. Now let's
go back to the גמרא. Gemara. Where are we? Okay. You're assuming
that the חזרת הש"ץ, Chazarat HaShatz, right? Because why's everybody bowing down
at the same time? Why's everybody bowing down at the same time?
Right. Yeah, yeah, yeah, yes. Absolutely. And the same with the קדושה.
Kedushah. Right, we're all talking about the חזרת הש"ץ. Chazarat HaShatz. Anyway,
תוספות Tosafot also quotes an interesting ירושלמי Yerushalmi that's interesting that also,
here the focus is on מודים Modim and the קדושה. Kedushah. ירושלמי
Yerushalmi is interested in the ברכה Berachah of שומע תפילה, Shomeia Tefillah,
which you know, comes a bit before מודים. Modim. That's also like
a key time to be participating in. So this becomes like very
important in terms of thinking about like what are those key ציבור
tzibbur experiences? קדושה, Kedushah, מודים, Modim, יהא שמיה רבא, Yehei Shemei Rabba,
the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, the ברכה Berachah of שומע תפילה Shomeia Tefillah is
a critical ברכה Berachah and so on. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: רבי יהודה אומר מברך לפניהם ולאחריהם. Rabbi Yehuda
omer mevarech lifnehem ve-achareihem. Now we finally get back to the issue
that was a very relevant and conceptually rich issue around תפילה, tefillah,
but now we get back to the issue about the בעל קרי.
ba'al keri. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you מברך לפניהם ולאחריהם.
mevarech lifnehem ve-achareihem. You do the ברכות berachot before and after the
שמע, Shema, no problem, or even though you're a בעל קרי. ba'al
keri. So let's take a look at this. Or the before and
after the food. He's not concerned about the בעל קרי ba'al keri
fact. So let's take a look. למימרא דסבר רבי יהודה בעל קרי
מותר בדברי תורה? Le-meimra de-savar Rabbi Yehuda ba'al keri mutar be-divrei Torah?
So this says like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is rejecting the whole
problem, that even somebody who is a בעל קרי ba'al keri can
learn תורה Torah and say God's name and so on. ואמר רבי
יהושע בן לוי מניין לבעל קרי שאסור בדברי תורה? Ve-amar Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi: Minayin le-ba'al keri she-assur be-divrei Torah? How do you know
בעל קרי ba'al keri is forbidden in תורה? Torah? שנאמר והודעתם לבניך
ולבני בניך, Shene'emar: Ve-hodatam le-vanecha ve-livnei vanecha, you shall inform these teachers
the תורה Torah to your children and your children's children. וסמיך ליה,
ve-samich lei, and it juxtaposes to this: יום אשר עמדת לפני ה'
אלהיך בחורב, Yom asher amadta lifnei Hashem Elokecha be-Chorev, the day you
stood at הר סיני. Har Sinai. So the same way the experience
of הר סיני Har Sinai was as we mentioned the other day,
did not want people that had just had sex, men or women
that had had semen coming out of their bodies and so on,
that that was seen as inappropriate. So therefore for all learning of
תורה, Torah, all learning of תורה Torah is a type of a
recreation of הר סיני Har Sinai and therefore you should not be,
a בעל קרי ba'al keri should not be doing it. Interestingly, like
even a ברכה Berachah is considered to be in that category, right?
A ברכה Berachah before דאוונען davening and before food, any saying of
God's name. So that's, so the גמרא Gemara says: Isn't this like
a universal principle? So doesn't רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda agree with it?
So the גמרא Gemara says: וכי תימא רבי יהודה לא דריש סמוכין?
Ve-chi teima Rabbi Yehuda lo darish smuchin? Yeah, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
is not impressed by the juxtaposition. Okay, so it juxtaposes תורה Torah
with הר סיני. Har Sinai. It doesn't mean every תורה Torah has
to be a הר סיני Har Sinai experience. If that's true, he
says that והאמר רב יוסף, ve-ha'amar Rav Yosef, but didn't רב יוסף
Rav Yosef say: אפילו מאן דלא דריש סמוכין בכל התורה במשנה תורה
דריש? afilu man de-lo darish smuchin be-chol ha-Torah, be-Mishneh Torah darish? Even
somebody that normally does not give significance to things being juxtaposed does
give that significance when it occurs in דברים, Devarim, in משנה תורה.
Mishneh Torah. Why is this? It's an interesting שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet
here on ברכות Berachot that says that since משה Moshe basically took
what was said earlier and restated it in דברים, Devarim, so if
he's reorganizing the material, there's gotta be significance in his reorganization. So
the fact that he chose to juxtapose certain things had to be
to give a particular message, so there's significance in the juxtaposition. Of
course you could make the same claim about the original time it
was written. Anytime you write something there's significance in how you're framing
it and the juxtaposition, but nevertheless here's an interesting approach that somehow
we give more attention to the way certain things are framed in
דברים Devarim and the particular sort of literary aspects for halakhic דרשות.
derashot. So the סמוכין smuchin even generally you don't give it halakhically
significant, in דברים Devarim it is. So we give more halakhic significance
to the literary decisions of a human being than to the literary
decisions of the אייבישטער. Eibeshter. Exactly. But what's beautiful about that is
it's on the one hand obviously ironic, but what's beautiful about that
is that this is part of the whole תורה שבעל פה Torah
SheBa'al Peh process, right? The whole point about getting significance is giving
halakhic תורה שבעל פה Torah SheBa'al Peh significance, and דברים Devarim is
like the nexus. It's a beautiful, I wrote this in a פרשה.
parsha. of תורה שבעל פה. Torah Shebe'al Peh. You have משה Moshe
reframing and restating the תורה. Torah. So it's essentially it is this
it is already a beginning of תורה שבעל פה Torah Shebe'al Peh
is דברים. Devarim. So anyway, so we דרשן darshan סמוכים smuchim in
דברים. Devarim. So the גמרא Gemara says והא רב יהודה אבתר סמוכי,
Veha Rav Yehuda avatar smuchi, therefore רב יהודה Rav Yehuda should give
significance to this. במשנה תורה דרש Be'mishneh Torah darash רב יהודה, Rav
Yehuda, and this is actually specifically about רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, דריב
יהודה לא דרש סמוכים בכל התורה כולה. de'Rav Yehuda lo darash smuchim
bechol haTorah kullah. Normally רב יהודה Rav Yehuda does not give significance
to juxtapositions. ובמשנה תורה דרש, Uve'mishneh Torah darash, but in דברים Devarim
he does. ובכל התורה כולה מנלן דלא דרש, Uvechol haTorah kullah minalan
delo darash, where do you know he does not? דתניא בן עזאי
אומר נאמר מכשפה לא תחיה. Detanya Ben Azzai omer ne'emar mechashefah lo
techayeh. Do not allow a witch to live. ונאמר, Vene'emar, so what
type of execution do you do? It's not clear what the form
of מיתה mitah is. שנאמר כל שוכב עם בהמה מות יומת. Shene'emar
kol shochev im behemah mot yumat. And then the immediate next פסוק
pasuk is, anybody that sleeps with an animal shall be put to
death. So that's juxtaposed. סמכו ענין לו, Samchu inyan lo, the two
things were juxtaposed לומר lomar to tell you, מה שוכב עם בהמה
בסקילה mah shochev im behemah biskilah the same way we know from
elsewhere that you stone a person who acts in an act of
bestiality, אף מכשפה נמי בסקילה. af mechashefah nami biskilah. So similarly for
witchcraft, it's stoning. We learn it from juxtaposition. אמר ליה רב יהודה,
Amar lei Rav Yehuda, so רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said to בן
עזאי, Ben Azzai, וכי מפני שסמכו ענין לו נוציא לזה בסקילה? vechi
mipnei shesamchu inyan lo notzi lazeh biskilah? Just because they're juxtaposed we
should go and stone the guy? So obviously we're going to kill
him anyway, but stoning is the worst of the מיתות, mitos, so
why should we? I'm not I'm not persuaded that the juxtaposition should
tell me such a הלכה. halacha. אלא, Ella, here's how I know.
I agree with you for the law, but I learn it a
different way. אוב וידעוני בכלל כל המכשפים היו. Ov ve'yidoni bichlal kol
hamechashefim hayu. אוב Ov and ידעוני yidoni are two forms of a
type of necromancy and witchcraft, and they were in the category of
to execute, not to let a witch to live. ולמה יצאו, Velamah
yatzu, why were they singled out? And it said specifically by them
that they're put to death להקיש להם lehakkish lahem to connect to
them, ולומר מה אוב וידעוני בסקילה, velomar mah ov ve'yidoni biskilah, the
same way the תורה Torah says explicitly by אוב Ov and ידעוני
yidoni that you stone them, אף מכשפה בסקילה. af mechashefah biskilah. So
it's not just because of juxtaposition because we actually know that certain
members of this class of מכשפה mechashefah is בסקילה, biskilah, that informs
on the whole class. That's a more rational argument, logical argument than
just the issue of juxtaposition. Anyway, so you see that רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda normally is not impressed by juxtaposition. ובמשנה תורה מנלן דדרש,
Uve'mishneh Torah minalan dedarash, and how do you know though in דברים
Devarim he does do this? דתניא רבי אליעזר אומר, Detanya Rabbi Eliezer
omer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said, נושא אדם אנוסת אביו ומפוטת אביו,
noseh adam anusat aviv umefutat aviv, אנוסת בנו ומפוטת בנו. anusat beno
umefutat beno. A person can marry his father's wife even after divorce,
a woman that his father was married to, but a man can
marry a woman that his father has had sex with. Now how
does the גמרא Gemara describe having sex with? It gives two scenarios,
a woman that his father has raped, or a woman that his
father has seduced. Right. So but basically Bobby, what are you upset
about? These this does happen. Nobody is condoning this. The question is
is that a man is forbidden to marry a previous wife of
his father's, but not a woman that his father has had sex
with, however whether it is rape or or otherwise, that is not
forbidden. Yes. In the ancient world when a new king would take
over, even if it's the son of the previous king, one of
the first things the new king would do would have sex with
all of the women of the father's harem. Aha. Okay. This is
clearly אסור assur for us. There you go. But only if he
was married to them. If he wasn't married to them it's permissible.
So how do you know that that is forbidden? ואמר רב גידל,
Ve'amar Rav Gidel, so and similarly by a man can do it
for for women his son has had sex with as long as
his son was never married to them. ואמר רב גידל אמר רב,
Ve'amar Rav Gidel amar Rav, מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה? mai ta'ama de'Rabbi
Yehuda? Where do you know this? דכתיב, Dechtiv, the verse says לא
יקח איש את אשת אביו, lo yikach ish et eshet aviv, a
man cannot marry his father's wife, ולא יגלה כנף אביו, velo yigaleh
knaf aviv, and cannot expose the sort of skirts, you know, of
the of his father's cloak. כנף שראה אביו לא יגלה. Knaf sherah
aviv lo yigaleh. So, I'm sorry did I skip a line? I
skipped a line. So the first position is a man can marry
such a woman. רבי יהודה אוסר באנוסת אביו ומפוטת אביו. Rabbi Yehuda
oser be'anusat aviv umefutat aviv. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says by a
woman that a man's son has had sex with, the father can
marry, but a woman that the father has had sex with, the
son cannot marry. Why not? Why can a son not marry a
woman his father has had sex with? מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's
the reason? דדרש רב יהודה דכתיב, de'darash Rav Yehuda dechtiv, לא יקח
איש את אשת אביו ולא יגלה כנף אביו. lo yikach ish et
eshet aviv velo yigaleh knaf aviv. So what does it mean the
skirt of the father? כנף שראה אביו, Knaf sherah aviv, the the
skirt that saw his father, meaning any woman who has had carnal
relations with his father, לא יגלה lo yigaleh he cannot expose, he
cannot have sex with such a woman. וממאי דבאנוסת אביו כתיב, Umimai
de've'anusat aviv ktiv, and how do you know that that's really what
it's talking that a woman his father has raped or has had
sex with otherwise? דסמיך ליה Desamich lay ונתן האיש השוכב עמה, Venasan
ha'ish hashochev imah, the immediate next פרשה parshah that's juxtaposed is about
a case of rape and the payment that's done for the rape.
So that tells him that this verse of what's prohibited with a
man with his woman that his father has slept with includes not
only a wife, but any woman his father slept with, even rape,
based on the juxtaposition. Anybody want to show some of these men?
Well, okay, so, אמרי Amrei anyway, let's just finish this point. You
see that Rabbi Yehuda is influenced by סמוכים, smuchim, so back to
the question. Why does he let all this together, why does he
let a בעל קרי ba'al keri learn Torah? We learned about Torah
learning קרא kera by juxtaposing הר סיני Har Sinai to learning Torah.
Rabbi Yehuda should agree to that juxtaposition. Why does he allow a
בעל קרי ba'al keri to learn Torah? So the answer is, and
with this we'll end for today, אין, In, the משנה תורה דורש,
Mishneh Torah doresh, yes, in דברים Devarim he does look at juxtapositions,
והני סמוכים מיבעי ליה לכדרבי יהושע בן לוי, vahani smuchim mibayei lay
lechideRabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, but this juxtaposition is not to tell you
that every learning Torah is the הר סיני Har Sinai experience, it's
to tell you something like Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi said. דאמר רבי
יהושע בן לוי, De'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, כל המלמד את בנו
תורה, kol hamelamed es bno Torah, מעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו קיבלה מהר
חורב. ma'aleh alav hakesuv k'ilu kibelah me'Har Chorev. If you teach Torah,
it's as if you received the Torah from הר חורב, Har Chorev,
שנאמר shenemar והודעתם לבניך ולבני בניך vehoda'atam levanecha ulevnei vanecha וכתיב בתריה
uchsiv basrei יום אשר עמדת לפני ה' אלהיך בחורב. yom asher amadta
lifnei Hashem Elokecha beChorev. So yes, is Torah like הר סיני? Har
Sinai? It's like הר סיני Har Sinai in the sense that if
you not only learn Torah, but teach Torah, and by the way
that's the power, you pass it down. We received the Torah from
God, so we have to now be part of the chain. If
you continue the chain and you pass it down, then it's like
you are reliving and you are like receiving the Torah from הר
סיני Har Sinai and now being part of that chain. That's what
it tells you. But it's not telling you that you have to
approach Torah in the same frame of body and mind that you
did at הר סיני Har Sinai and therefore you do not have
to worry about the בעל קרי ba'al keri experience. So we will
see more of this tomorrow.